Greetings!
Andrzej Tomecki.
I invite you to watch the movie.
I hope that it will be interesting.
Gothic II: the History of Khorinis
Andrzej Tomecki - A legend from the culture world. Narrator - Piotr Borowiec.
Andrzej Tomecki is an absolutely iconic person - an actor, without which we can't imagine the existence of Gothic in polish version.
Born in 1932, he grown up and was raised in the pre-war Warsaw.
As twelve year old liaison, he participated in the Warsaw Uprising.
After the war and gratuated high-school certificate, he decided to study in Panstwowa Wyższa Szkoła Teatralna in Warsaw, which graduated in 1956.
He made a debut in a theatre just when he was a student - appearing on the stages
of the most prestigious warsaw scenes - for example 'Teatr Powszechni', 'Operetta' or on 'Targówka'.
He combined a stage career with musical activity, by earning the audience prize on the festivan in Opole in 1967.
He was also a performer of hit called "Jump".
He is known also from various movie roles - including Glaukos the physician in the 'Quo Vadis'.
'I don't even know, where she found a shelter.
She has left, Sire, when you have been absent.
Crispus...
Crispus is hiding her from me all over again, he doesn't trust me.
No Sire. Ligia has decided herself, and Crispus has been deprecated
by Peter the Apostle for that he had a grudge to Ligia, because she loves you.'
In the world of dubbing he is known from participation in many movies, radio plays, polish radio theaters and computer games.
In Diablo II: Lord of Destruction he personated the Druid class.
'Baal... Join to your brothers and begone into oblivion!'
In Icewind Dale II he provided a voice to Oswald Fiddlebender.
'My name's Fiddlebender. Oswald, that is.
Well, Fiddlebender's my *last* name, my first name is Oswald
so it's Oswald Fiddlebender. A pleasure to meet you.'
He also dubbed Jack Beretto - a protagonist of Chicago 1930.
A game of the creators of a very rated Robin Hood: Legend of Sherwood.
'Palace Hotel? Nice!
Welcome in the Palace Hotel Mr. Beretto!
With regards from Don Falcone.'
But the biggest and the longest episode in his dubbing career was the roles in the first games of Gothic saga!
In the first Gothic he dubbed the most iconic characters - ahead with Torlof:
'I'm Torlof. I was involved in a mutiny as mate of a royal warship.
It wasn't such a good idea. The greater part of the crew was on the captain's side.'
or also the old digger - Grimes:
'I saw the faces of those who tried to get out of the Barrier. Don't make the same mistake,
the Barrier will stop everybody.'
and Gilbert:
'What are you doing here? Don't often get visitors up here, he he!
Very clever of you to find my hiding place.'
and Torrez - the Fire Magician:
'How's venturing in the magic arts?
That's none of your business!'
In Gothic II he dubbed, by conrast, another iconic characters - including Lothar:
'What!? You are not even a member of the City Guard!
You are not even a citizen!
How did you come up that you could bear Paladin's armor?'
or Sekob:
'Go to work, then maybe some day you can call a piece of land your own. But until then, kindly loaf around somewhere else.'
Thereafter in the addon 'the Night of the Raven' he voiced an unforgettable character of captain Greg:
'You'll have to forgive an ignorant old seaman. I'm a stranger in these parts and I don't really know all the rules.'
'Are you still having problems with the city guards?
I'll GIVE you problems, you punk.'
Although he is 85 years old, he still stays in fine shape as well being active on the labour market.
Despite the fact that two of his characters of Gothic game will appear in the first part of 'the History of Khorinis',
we couldn't imagine his absence in the cast of our project!
Well, we should probably start from the beginning.
I was born a long time ago - before the war.
I lived in the Downtown, where we are here at this very moment.
What is more funny, during the Warsaw Uprising (Polish: Powstanie Warszawskie) was being cathed by the signal
which began the Uprising. Not so far - on Hoża St. It was five o'clock.
There was not a possibility to come back to home,
because we were living on the Savior's Square.
So I was spending a night at my friend's.
Because a returning to my house was still impossible,
I was spending a night at my friend's house almost whole week.
Later, with the fact that telephones worked, I called to my father and he came for me on Krucza St.
to take me back to our home.
And then we were coming back from Krucza St. through Wilcza St.
More funny is a fact that now I live on Wilcza St.
We got to Marszałkowska St., in the corner of Wilcza and Marszałkowska we were seeing a collapsed trolley.
It was used as a barricade.
A german soldier was shooting from the Saviour's Square side.
And from time to time, somebody who jumped the barricade was shot.
We were managing to jump the barricade with my father.
I was twelve years old. For me - a little lad - a participation in some war was
a sensation, an attraction.
As a result, I was volunteering to the Home Army (translator's postscript: Polish: Armia Krajowa) and I was liaison -
a dogsbody.
I had an ID card, a band - all attributes of an insurgent.
What I had to do - for example I had to go to the Saviour's church for host (translator's postscript: communion wafer, also sacramental wafer).
and because a priest celebrated mass on 6th of August St.,
it was necessary to bring that host.
Our outpost was in the corner of Polna and Mokotowska, on the top of five or six story building,
I don't remember exactly.
There were a crew of machine gun, an ordinary Mauser. Two, or maybe three friends of mine had a watch there.
I came some day to them and they said - 'Hey, take this rifle
and try to aim towards Lubelska Union's square.
There, there were Germans who loitered around a building of the Firewatch.
'Try to shoot, perhaps you'll hit him'
I tried.
I don't know if I shot him, but they claimed that I had done it.
Of course I was happy and I said about it in the headquarters - I received title of a rifleman.
Later I was taking a part in watching Germans on Mokotowska St., who were building a barricade on that street.
Sitting in the window and watching over German prisoners, and they were dressed in uniforms - it's important,
because a motorbike was arriving through Polna St. in a moment. It seems that they arrived from beyond Warsaw,
they were coming to those fellow-captives, trying to get an information.
Of course we were happy, because we arrested them
and we had not only those, who were building the barricade, but also those two who had arrived. With the motorbike as well.
A message reached to our headquarters, that at Lardelly's - in the famous baker's placed in the corner of Polna and Mokotowska -
was a group of Germans, it would be worth to get rid of them.
A dozen of our boys was volunterring that they will go there and do it. So they went.
However, they didn't predict that Germans had hidden
in a balcony inside the building.
And when our people was entering to the building
they got caught in the Germans' crossfire,
who were watching over their outpost.
And unfortunately, everyone died.
It wasn't necessary.
The Uprising lasted insofar as lasted,
somehow we got through it with my parents,
we survived despite bombardment of
the Downtown.
We were coming out on 4th of October 1944
through the 6th of August St.,
in which was an exit passage from Warsaw.
A crowd of people. It was of course very sad moment -
I wanted to leave Warsaw with the insurgents,
but my parents didn't allow to go with them.
As a twelve year old boy I had to agree to this.
They were taking us to the Western Station.
There we were getting into goods wagon and we were going towards Ursus (translator's postscript: a city next to Warsaw) and there we were stopping.
They were ordering us to get out. I saw a people, who were jumping through the railways
and escaping, because Germans didn't always stay there.
And we were going with a huge group before the Ursus factory
and they were ordering us to wait there.
At some point, my father said "I'll go away for a while.'
And he indeed went away. Later it turned out, that he used a very long grass, cereals, which were on the field.
He jumped in those cereals and went away.
He left us.
After four days of our stay in the camp, there was a selection.
A huge gate and leaving people through it.
A german soldier was staying in the middle of that gate, who was directing people -
to the left, to the right, to the left, to the right...
We were leaving with my mother as almost the last. Before us, our neighbours had left through the gate.
We see that our neighbors are taking the left, so we are also taking the left.
German soldier says: "No, to the right.", but we wanted to the left.
"No, to the right."
Later it turned out, that those from the left side were going to Germany. We were from the right side.
They transported us to Kielce and there they released us from the wagons, do what you want.
And so it's the end of the Uprising story.
Later we finally met with my father.
My parents had decided that they won't return to the collapsed Warsaw, because we have nothing there.
Our house was not existing anymore, so we were going to Inowrocław on the west side of Poland and we were starting live there.
There I performed in the theatre for the first time -
in the school theatre,
but soon after the spectacle, a review was published in a local press.
In that review two names were mentioned:
my friend Marysia Ciesielska, who is a great actress
and me.
'Those are two names, who will for sure meet in the future'
If somebody wrote in this way, it must have happened, because later when I was going to the school in Aleksandrów Kujawski,
to Salesians - it was a great dormitory and Salesian's school, which it exists to this day.
And there I portrayed Judas for the first time.
It is very funny, because I don't know why but my life has bonded with that character.
A theatre school, four years, glorious fellows:
Zbigniew Zapasiewicz
Andrzej Żarnecki, Janek Matiaskiewicz
Wanda Majerówna
Anna Ciepielewska - a pack of cool people.
What happened with us later?
We split out, despite promising that we would be in some group.
But there were only a mere promises, later a life made, that our fates have turned out differently.
I have worked in the Teatr Powszechny for four years after the theatre school.
I played a lot.
Indeed I had a lucky, that I got roles.
'Gentlemen, silence, please?
Mister Nowacki
Mister Nowacki.
Here, here, Mister Engineer seems to be nervous.
Was the food tasty?
Mister Nowacki, there are always some arguments here, what are you giving people to eat?
I give what they give me - there are no miracles.
After that I changed a theater program, because I suddenly got a proposition to the Warsaw operetta.
I portrayed a big role in the operetta.
I was there two years. After that there was the "Syrena". And that's why I desired to appear on stage.
When they had proposed me a participation on the festival in Opole,
to sing a song,
I risked, because in the Common Theater (Polish: Teatr Powszechny) I sang as well.
But I tasted in songs and stages, because suddenly I had got a proposition to 'Wagabunda' -
a cabaret founded by Lidia Wysocka, in which Boguś Kobiela was there,
also Maria Wysocka,
and Lidia Wysocka,
and Marian Załódzki.
We were travelling with programme through Poland.
Month by month, two-three weeks.
And I tasted in it that I had thought that I could make a programme myself
and go with him abroad.
It was difficult to go abroad.
I made a programme about Warsaw.
The programme, which lasts an hour and half,
it includes 22 songs,
a poetry,
some anecdotes.
Everything was happening on the background of photos of Warsaw, because
that was the title of my programme - 'And here is Warsaw'
Every song was about Warsaw, or people living in Warsaw,
Szymon Kobyliński was making a very beautiful drawings,
which were displayed on a screen.
And it is very funny, because when I was organizing that programme I met with a lot of awesome people,
who helped me in organizing that programme.
A factory made for example a rack for a screen,
because I had my own screen.
Reception of programme was positive, because I played a premiere in cafe on Piękna St.
It turned out, that ot is a very good programme.
'Therefore you can go abroad, if you want'
But how?
After all, somebody must invite us and organize everything abroad.
And it comes to my mind, that programme could be made in esperanto language,
so in the language, which would be easy to show in various countries,
not only in one.
I made that programme in esperanto and I was singing and I was reciting poetry in esperanto.
And we got in the car in 1970. I said 'we', because together - with my wife,
who as a doctor made a three years break from work and she accompanied me in the journey through Europe
with that programme.
A very funny story.
A premiere was to take place in Vienna.
We are entering to the Polish-Czech border and Polish customs says
'Wait, you have not a permission to have the tapes',
and on those tapes is music to my songs.
I say ' What should I do now?'
'You should go to the management, to Katowice.
Perhaps they will give you a permission, but you must have it.'
I say 'Hold on, perhaps I'll show you. I'll record
some songs, I'll sing you and you will know, what is it?'
So what was turned out? The border has been closed,
all customs have come to the concert,
and I've been singing for half an hour.
When they heard, they said 'You can go'.
And so, we arrived to Vienna and we gave a premiere.
And from there our journey throughout the Europe began.
Later was Italy, Tunesia, and then again Italy,
Switzerland, Germany,
France.
We got an invitation to the esperantists' congress in London.
We were arriving there.
We were playing in a beautiful theatrical hall
for 700 people.
After the concert
we got invitations from various countries:
Japan, Australia.
All we do is arrive, but how?
We have tried to get an australian visa just in case.
And we got them,
but it turned out, that in the australian government is the esperantists.
So he must support his people.
We didn't arrive, neither to Australia, nor to Japan.
However, the Ministry of Culture - recognising that our programme is interesing - is making a good advertasting in Poland and in Warsaw.
We did it.
One day we got, with the car,
on the 'Batory'
and we have sailed to Montreal for 11 days.
We started our journey from Montreal,
then it was Toronto,
and Ottawa on the road.
We had a pretty concert in the nursing home for Poles in Montreal.
After the concert, an old lady came to us
and she said 'Thank you.
I even kissed the car from Warsaw.'
What is more funny, organizing a concert there was not so easy,
because I had to do it myself - I hadn't an organizer.
I called for example to some polish organization
that 'maybe I perform a concert for you?'.
'Yes, very well.'
'Have you got a concert here?'
'Yes, in the other organization.'
'No, if you perform there, you will not perform a concert in our organization.'
The so-called, unfortunately, 'a little polish hell'.
Fortunately we hadn't to perform there, so we were going further.
Later was Detroid,
Chicago,
Milwaukee.
Coming back from Chicago
to New York City, we passed through the highway near Cleveland,
and because I had a phone numer to Polish radio in Cleveland,
we stopped on the highway and I phoned,
from the phone box.
A telephone was picked by the owner of that radio,
and she asks 'Who is calling?'.
Of course I said: 'Andrzej Tomecki.'
She says: 'Wait,
what Tomecki?'
I played your song yesterday.'
'What song?'
'I got recordings of your songs and I played it in the radio
and you suddenly appear.'
I say 'That's right, I'm here, I'm going to NYC
with that programme.'
'You can perform it for us.
In addition I'm organizing a collection for the Warsaw castle.'
'The more reason that we can play for you.'
And the concert was organized within two days,
on which was even the mayor of Cleveland,
who congratulated and thanked me.
They collected over 1000$, which were transferred
to a Warsaw bank account .
New Your City. There were many attractions.
We lived at Russian woman,
who graduated 'The Juilliard School'
with distinction. A great pianists,
in her mid-60s.
She helped us by renting a room.
And we have lived there for two months. Thanks to her, we hadn't to pay for renting a house.
We were helping her in running household.
She was very amusing and she was lovable as well.
She lived there alone
with kitty.
The kitty was befriended to her
so there were plays all the time.
The kitty were hiding for example behind a wardrobe,
and Ester was going around the apartment and she was screaming
'Where is she? Where is she?'
But a consequence of this was a story, which was related to us, namely
Ester has been away for few days to concerts
and we stayed with that kitty alone.
We had a concert a twenty-something kilometers away from New York City.
We arrived late,
somewhere at first-two o'clock.
We opened the door,
and the kitty sits and greets us.
And just now our story begins -
I wear a costume,
smoking,
after the concert, I haven't changed clothes yet,
and the kitty demands a play.
And I have to jump and call "Where is she? Where is she?' - just like an idiot.
Our housekeeper, at which we've lived in NYC
was organizing us a free parties from time to time.
Namely invitations to opera,
an invitation to Carnegie Hall.
About Carnegie Hall.
We are coming back from the Carnegie Hall,
it's cold:
-2 or -3 degrees of Celsius,
an evening.
We are getting on Broadway
we are enetering to the car: a silence,
the car is not working.
It must be pushed.
Fortunately Citroen is so leight car that
it is possible to push him.
And what are we doing?
I am at the wheel,
and my wife is pushing it.
It had to be a funny view,
a hillarious and attractive,
especially to Americans,
because they are always surprised.
But the woman, who is pushing a car
through Broadway
is a big sensation.
NYC has ended to us very nasty, because
someone had stolen us prior to departure.
Everything had been packed up in our car.
We came to our car, in order to departure,
and on our car lied our screen, a door was opened,
two suitcases
with microphones -
they've gone.
Fortunately
we had a contact with an owner of
travel agency,
who had even proposed us in the beginning of our stay,
that he will organize a cycle of concerts of that show,
on the american universities.
On condition that I will make a half of show in English language.
But it must be translated.
Translating songs is not so easy.
With poetry is a little easier,
but we need Barańczak to do this as well.
Fortunately he helped us by
buying the microphones for us,
an amplifier and he included all of this in the costs.
He saved us, because we had a journey to Canada.
There,
we had some concerts,
later in Montreal,
where the "Batory" was expecting us.
We got on the "Batory"
and we were sailing to Poland.
'What, did she taunt you?
She tired me... She went to my bed herself.
She was glorious.
She said, that she had finally met someone, who would understand her.
After few weeks I was boozed.
She said, that she regretted
that she had had two guys before me'.
What was later?
It was 1973 - 1974.
I was involved in the theatre on Targówka.
Today is called 'Rampa'.
Marian Jonkajtys - my friend
was organizing then a completely fresh team as a director, a frest theatre.
But
besides theatrical work
I worked a lot in Polish Radio -
I have cooperated since 1950.
From the radio I began to work in dubbing.
The dubbing turned out
to be a difficult discipline.
The more easier was computer games,
becuase it wasn't necessary to 'hit' precisely
in a picture,
only then it was assembled differently.
Anyway, it was more easier to me.
That dubbing was a quite difficult
element.
And so I 'earned' my retirement.
I dubbed in two parts of Gothic saga
and also in the addon - 'the Night of the Raven'
For me it was a pleasure, but I barely remember that period.
And on a retirement you never know what will happen.
Once is something interesting
in our profession, because until man lives, he can do something.
Some radio, some dubbing, some games.
Best regards to all fans
of mine
and Gothic.
Take care yourselves!
Directed by - Piotr Czołnowski
Director of Photography - Lechosław Czołnowski
Edited by - Mateusz Pawłowski
Sound - Maciej Amilkiewicz, Correction - Szymon Nawrocki
English subtitles: Bartosz ‘Kereth’ Biały. Correction and adaptation: Szymon Żak. Based on Polish subtitles made by Szymon Żak.